So when I was in Morocco,
عندما كنت في المغرب ,
in Casablanca, not so long ago,
في الدار البيضاء , ليس منذ وقت طويل ,
I met a young unmarried mother called Faiza.
التقيت أماً شابة غير متزوجة اسمها فايزة .
Faiza showed me photos of her infant son
أرتني صوراً لابنها الرضيع
and she told me the story of his conception, pregnancy, and delivery.
وأخبرتني قصة تخلقه وفترة حملها به وولادته .
It was a remarkable tale,
كانت قصة ملفتة للنظر ,
but Faiza saved the best for last.
ولكن فايزة ادخرت الأفضل إلى النهاية .
"You know, I am a virgin," she told me.
قالت لي :" أنا عذراء "
"I have two medical certificates to prove it."
"عندي شهادتين طبيتين تثبتان ذلك "
This is the modern Middle East,
هذا هو الشرق الأوسط الحديث ,
where two millennia after the coming of Christ,
حيث بعد ألفي سنة من ولادة المسيح ,
virgin births are still a fact of life.
لا تزال ولادة العذراء حقيقة من حقائق الحياة .
Faiza's story is just one of hundreds I've heard over the years, traveling across the Arab region
قصة فايزة هي قصة واحدة فقط من مئات القصص التي سمعتها على مر السنين خلال سفري في أقطاب المنطقة العربية
talking to people about sex.
وأنا أتحدث مع الناس عن الجنس .
Now, I know this might sound like a dream job,
الآن , أعرف أن هذا العمل يمكن أن يبدو حلما ,
or possibly a highly dubious occupation,
أو ربما عمل مشكوك فيه للغاية ,
but for me, it's something else altogether.
ولكن بالنسبة لي هو شيء مختلف تماما .
I'm half Egyptian, and I'm Muslim.
أنا مسلمة ونصف مصرية .
But I grew up in Canada, far from my Arab roots.
ولكنني ترعرعت في كندا , بعيدا عن جذوري العربية .
Like so many who straddle East and West,
كالعديدين الذين ينتشرون شرقا وغربا ,
I've been drawn, over the years, to try to better understand my origins.
خططت على مر السنين لأحاول تحسين فهمي لأصولي .
That I chose to look at sex comes from my background in HIV/AIDS,
اختياري البحث في الجنس جاء من خلفيتي السابقة عن فيروس نقص المناعة المكتسبة / الإيدز ,
as a writer and a researcher and an activist.
ككاتبة وباحثة وناشطة .
Sex lies at the heart of an emerging epidemic in the Middle East and North Africa,
يقع الجنس في قلب الأوبئة المنتشرة في الشرق الأوسط وشمال افريقية ,
which is one of only two regions in the world where HIV/AIDS is still on the rise.
التي تعد واحدة من منطقتين فقط في العالم التي لا يزال فيها مرض الإيدز في ازدياد .
Now sexuality is an incredibly powerful lens
الحياة الجنسية حاليا هي عدسة قوية ملتصقة بشكل لا يصدق
with which to study any society,
مع دراسة اي مجتمع ,
because what happens in our intimate lives
لأن ما يحدث في حياتنا الحميمية
is reflected by forces on a bigger stage:
منعكس حتما على مسرح أكبر :
in politics and economics, in religion and tradition, in gender and generations.
في السياسة والاقتصاد , في الدين والعادات , في النوع والذرية .
As I found, if you really want to know a people,
كما وجدت , إذا أردت أن تعرف الناس حقا ,
you start by looking inside their bedrooms.
ابدأ بالنظر في غرف نومهم .
Now to be sure, the Arab world is vast and varied.
لنكون متأكدين , العالم العربي كبير ومتنوع .
But running across it are three red lines --
ولكن يتخلله ثلاث خطوط حمراء --
these are topics you are not supposed to challenge in word or deed.
هذه المواضيع من غير المفترض منك أن تتحداها لا بالكلمة ولا بالفعل .
The first of these is politics.
الموضوع الأول هو السياسة .
But the Arab Spring has changed all that,
ولكن الربيع العربي غير كل ذلك ,
in uprisings which have blossomed across the region since 2011.
في الانتفاضات التي ازدهرت في أنحاء المنطقة منذ عام 2011 .
Now while those in power, old and new,
في حين حاليا أن من هم في السلطة ، القديمة والجديدة،
continue to cling to business as usual,
مستمرين بالتشبث بمكانهم كالمعتاد ,
millions are still pushing back,
لايزال الملايين يدحرون
and pushing forward to what they hope will be a better life.
ويمضون قدما للوصول لما تأملوه ستكون الحياة أفضل.
That second red line is religion.
والخط الأحمر الثاني هو الدين .
But now religion and politics are connected,
ولكن الدين والسياسة مرتبطتين ,
with the rise of such groups as the Muslim Brotherhood.
مع نشأة بعض الجماعات مثل الإخوان المسلمين .
And some people, at least, are starting to ask questions
وبعض الناس , على الأقل , بدأت تسأل أسئلةً
about the role of Islam in public and private life.
عن دور الإسلام في الحياة العامة والخاصة .
You know, as for that third red line, that off-limits subject,
كما تعلمون بالنسبة للخط الأحمر الثالث , وهذا خارج الموضوع ,
what do you think it might be?
برأيكم ماذا يمكن أن يكون ؟
Audience: Sex.
الجمهور : الجنس .
Shereen El Feki: Louder, I can't hear you.
شيرين الفقي : بصوت أعلى لم أسمعكم .
SEF: Again, please don't be shy.
شيرين : لو سمحتم مرة ثانية , لا تخجلوا .
Audience: Sex.
الجمهور : الجنس .
SEF: Absolutely, that's right, it's sex. (Laughter)
شيرين : حتما صحيح , إنه الجنس . (ضحك )
Across the Arab region, the only accepted context for sex is marriage --
في المنطقة العربية , المصطلح الوحيد المقبول للجنس هو الزواج --
approved by your parents, sanctioned by religion
والمقبول لدى والديك ويقره الدين
and registered by the state.
والمسجل من قِبل الدولة .
Marriage is your ticket to adulthood.
الزواج هو تذكرتك لمرحلة الرشد .
If you don't tie the knot, you can't move out of your parents' place,
إذا لم تعقد قرانك لا تستطيع الانتقال من منزل والديك .
and you're not supposed to be having sex,
ومن غير المفترض منك أن تمارس الجنس ,
and you're definitely not supposed to be having children.
وحتما من غير المفروض أن يكون لديك أولاد .
It's a social citadel; it's an impregnable fortress
انها القلعة الاجتماعية، بل حصنا منيعا
which resists any assault, any alternative.
الذي يقاوم أي اعتداء و أي بديل .
And around the fortress is this vast field of taboo
وحول هذه القلعة ميدان واسع من المحرمات
against premarital sex, against condoms,
ضد ممارسة الجنس قبل الزواج , ضد الواقي الذكري ,
against abortion, against homosexuality,
ضد الإجهاض , ضد المثلية الجنسية ,
you name it.
سمها ما شئت .
Faiza was living proof of this.
وكانت فايزة دليل حي على ذلك .
Her virginity statement was not a piece of wishful thinking.
وكان بيان عذريتها ليس شيء من التمني .
Although the major religions of the region extoll premarital chastity,
على الرغم من أن الأديان الرئيسية في المنطقة تقدس العفة قبل الزواج ،
in a patriarchy, boys will be boys.
في عالم الآباء الذكور يبقوا أولاداً .
Men have sex before marriage,
الذكر يمارس الجنس قبل الزواج ,
and people more or less turn a blind eye.
والناس تغض الطرف عنه بشكل أو بآخر .
Not so for women,
وليس المثل للمرأة ,
who are expected to be virgins on their wedding night --
التي من المتوقع أن تكون عذراء في ليلة زفافهما --
that is, to turn up with your hymen intact.
كل ذلك ليصل إلى غشاء البكارة السليم .
This is not a question of individual concern,
وهذه ليست مسألة قلق فردية ,
this is a matter of family honor, and in particular, men's honor.
وإنما مسألة شرف العائلة وشرف الرجل على وجه الخصوص .
And so women and their relatives
وهكذا فإن النساء وأقاربهم
will go to great lengths to preserve this tiny piece of anatomy --
يذهبون إلى أبعد مدى للحفاظ على هذه القطعة التشريحية الصغيرة--
from female genital mutilation,
من تشويه الأعضاء التناسلية الأنثوية
to virginity testing, to hymen repair surgery.
إلى اختبار العذرية , إلى إجراء عملية جراحية لإعادة غشاء البكارة .
Faiza chose a different route:
اختارت فايزة طريقا مختلفا :
non-vaginal sex.
الجماع الخارجي .
Only she became pregnant all the same.
إلا أنها أصبحت حاملاً كما في الطريقة المعتادة .
But Faiza didn't actually realize this,
ولكن فايزة لم تكن تدرك ذلك ,
because there's so little sexuality education in schools,
لأن الثقافة الجنسية في المدرسة ضئيلة جداً ,
and so little communication in the family.
والتواصل الأسري قليل أيضاً .
When her condition became hard to hide,
عندما أصبحت حالتها أصعب من أن تُخفى ,
Faiza's mother helped her flee her father and brothers.
ساعدتها أمها بالفرار من أبيها وأخوتها .
This is because honor killings are a real threat
ذلك لأن جرائم الشرف تعتبر تهديدا حقيقيا
for untold numbers of women in the Arab region.
لأعداد لا تحصى من النساء في المنطقة العربية .
And so when Faiza eventually fetched up at a hospital in Casablanca,
وفي نهاية المطاف عندما أُدخلت فايزة مستشفى في الدار البيضاء ,
the man who offered to help her,
الرجل الذي قدم لها المساعدة ,
instead tried to rape her.
عوضاً عن ذلك حاول اغتصابها .
Sadly, Faiza is not alone.
للأسف , فايزة ليست وحدها .
In Egypt, where my research is focused,
في مصر , حيث تتركز أبحاثي هناك ,
I have seen plenty of trouble in and out of the citadel.
رأيت الكثير من المشاكل داخل وخارج القلعة .
There are legions of young men
هناك كم هائل من الشباب
who can't afford to get married,
الذين لا يستطيعون الزواح ,
because marriage has become a very expensive proposition.
لأن الزواج أصبح مكلف جداً .
They are expected to bear the burden of costs in married life,
ومن المفترض منهم تحمل أعباء تكاليف الحياة الزوجية ,
but they can't find jobs.
لكنهم لم يتمكنوا من العثور على وظائف .
This is one of the major drivers of the recent uprisings,
وهذه واحدة من المحركات الرئيسية للانتفاضات الأخيرة ,
and it is one of the reasons for the rising age of marriage
وواحدة من أسباب ارتفاع سن الزواج
in much of the Arab region.
في معظم أنحاء المنطقة العربية .
There are career women who want to get married,
هناك نساء عاملات يرغبن بالزواج ,
but can't find a husband,
ولكنهن لا يتمكن من إيجاد زوجاً ,
because they defy gender expectations,
لأنهن يتحدين توقعات جنسهن ,
or as one young female doctor in Tunisia put it to me,
أو كما قالت لي طبيبة في تونس ,
"The women, they are becoming more and more open.
" أصبحت المرأة ء منفتحة أكثر وأكثر .
But the man, he is still at the prehistoric stage."
في حين الرجل لايزال في مرحلة ما قبل التاريخ . "
And then there are men and women who cross the heterosexual line,
وثم هناك رجال ونساء يتجاوزون خط الجنس الآخر ,
who have sex with their own sex,
الذين يمارسون الجنس مع أمثالهم ,
or who have a different gender identity.
أو الذين يحملون هوية جنسية مختلفة .
They are on the receiving end of laws which punish their activities,
هم على الطرف المتلقي من القوانين التي تُعاقب أنشطتهم ,
even their appearance.
وحتى مظهرهم .
And they face a daily struggle with social stigma,
ويواجهون صراعات يومية مع وصمة العار الاجتماعية ,
with family despair,
مع خيبة أمل العائلة ,
and with religious fire and brimstone.
ومع نار وكبريت دينية .
Now, it's not as if it's all rosy in the marital bed either.
الآن , انها ليست على حد سواء كما إن كانت وردية على فراش الزواج .
Couples who are looking for greater happiness,
الزوجين الذين يبحثون عن قدر أكبر من السعادة ,
greater sexual happiness in their married lives,
قدر أكبر من السعادة الجنسية في حياتهم الزوجية ,
but are at a loss of how to achieve it,
ولكنهم في حيرة في كيفية تحقيق ذلك ,
especially wives, who are afraid of being seen as bad women
وخصوصا الزوجات , اللواتي يخشين من أن ينظر إليهن على أنهن سيئات
if they show some spark in the bedroom.
إذا أظهروا بعضا من الحماس في غرفة النوم .
And then there are those whose marriages
ثم هناك تلك الزيجات
are actually a veil for prostitution.
التي هي في الواقع ستاراًعلى البغاء .
They have been sold by their families,
بيعت من قِبل أسرها ,
often to wealthy Arab tourists.
للسيّاح العرب الأثرياء غالباً .
This is just one face of a booming sex trade across the Arab region.
هذا فقط وجه واحد من تجارة الجنس المزدهرة في أنحاء المنطقة العربية .
Now raise your hand if any of this is sounding familiar to you,
الآن , ارفع يدك لو كانت واحدة من تلك مألوفة بالنسبة لك ,
from your part of the world.
من جزئك في هذا العالم .
Yeah. It's not as if the Arab world has a monopoly on sexual hangups.
نعم . إنها ليست كما لو أن العالم العربي عنده المونوبلي على الصعوبات الجنسية .
And although we don't yet have an Arab Kinsey Report
وعلى الرغم من أننا لا نملك حتى الآن تقرير لكينزي للعرب
to tell us exactly what's happening inside bedrooms across the Arab region,
ليخبرنا بالضبط ما يحدث داخل غرف نوم المنطقة العربية ,
It's pretty clear that something is not right.
من الواضح تماما أن ثمة شيء غير صحيح .
Double standards for men and women,
المعايير المزدوجة للرجل والمرأة ,
sex as a source of shame,
الجنس كمصدر للعار ,
family control limiting individual choices,
تحكّم الأسرة الذي يحد من الخيارات الفردية ,
and a vast gulf between appearance and reality:
وهوّة شاسعة بين المظهر والواقع :
what people are doing
ما يفعله الناس
and what they're willing to admit to,
والأمور التي عندهم استعداد للاعتراف بها ,
and a general reluctance to move beyond private whispers
وعزوف عام عن نقل الوسوسات الخاصة
to a serious and sustained public discussion.
إلى نقاشات جدية وعلنية مستديمة .
As one doctor in Cairo summed it up for me,
كما لخص لي أحد الأطباء في القاهرة ,
"Here, sex is the opposite of sport.
"هنا , الجنس عكس الرياضة .
Football, everybody talks about it,
الجميع يتحدث عن كرة القدم
but hardly anyone plays.
ولكن لا يكاد أي شخص يلعبها .
But sex, everybody is doing it,
بينما ممارسة الجنس الكل يقوم به
but nobody wants to talk about it." (Laughter)
ولكن لا أحد يرغب بالتكلم عنه " (ضحك )
(Music) (In Arabic)
( موسيقى ) ( باللغة العربية )
SEF: I want to give you a piece of advice,
شيرين : أريد أن أعطيكم نصيحة ,
which if you follow it, will make you happy in life.
وإذا اتبعتوها ستجعل حياتكم سعيدة .
When your husband reaches out to you,
عندما يصل زوجك إليك ,
when he seizes a part of your body,
عندما يستولي جزءاً من جسدك ,
sigh deeply and look at him lustily.
تنفسي الصعداء وانظري إليه بشهوة .
When he penetrates you with his penis,
عندما يتغلغل فيك بقضيبه ,
try to talk flirtatiously and move yourself in harmony with him.
حاولي أن تغازليه وتحركي نفسك بتناغم معه .
Hot stuff!
أمور الساخنة !
And it might sound that these handy hints
وقد يبدو أن هذه النصائح المفيدة
come from "The Joy of Sex" or YouPorn.
جاءت من "متعة الجنس " أو من يوبورن .
But in fact, they come from a 10th-century Arabic book
ولكنها في الحقيقة أتت من كتاب عربي يعود للقرن العاشر
called "The Encyclopedia of Pleasure,"
اسمه "موسوعة السعادة ,"
which covers sex from aphrodisiacs to zoophilia,
الذي يغطي مواضيع الجنس من المنشّطات إلى الولع بالحيوان ,
and everything in between.
وكل ما بين ذلك .
The Encyclopedia is just one in a long line of Arabic erotica,
هذه الموسوعة هي فقط واحدة من سلسلة طويلة من الأدب العربي المشكوف ,
much of it written by religious scholars.
كُتب أغلبها من قِبل علماء الدين .
Going right back to the Prophet Muhammad,
وبالعودة إلى النبي محمد ,
there is a rich tradition in Islam
فإن هناك تقليد عريق في الإسلام
of talking frankly about sex:
بالحديث عن الجنس صراحة :
not just its problems, but also its pleasures,
ليس فقط عن مشكلاته , وإنما عن متعته كذلك ,
and not just for men, but also for women.
وليس فقط للرجال وإنما للنساء أيضاً .
A thousand years ago, we used to have whole dictionaries of sex in Arabic.
منذ ألف سنة , لقد كان لدينا قواميس كاملة باللغة العربية عن الجنس .
Words to cover every conceivable sexual feature,
كلمات لتغطية كل ميزة جنسية يمكن تصورها ,
position and preference, a body of language
المواضع والتفضيلات , لغة الجسد
that was rich enough to make up the body of the woman you see on this page.
وكانت ثرية بما يكفي لجعلك ترى جسد المرأة في هذه الصفحة .
Today, this history is largely unknown in the Arab region.
اليوم , هذا التاريخ غير معروف إلى حد كبير في البلاد العربية .
Even by educated people, who often feel more comfortable talking about sex
حتى من قِبل المثقفين الذين غالبا ما يشعرون بمزيد من الراحة عند حديثهم عن الجنس
in a foreign language than they do in their own tongue.
بلغة أجنبية أكثر من راحتهم عندما يتحدثون عنه بلغتهم الأم .
Today's sexual landscape looks a lot like Europe and America
المشهد الجنسي اليوم يبدو مشابه تماما لأوربا وأمريكا
on the brink of the sexual revolution.
على حافة الثورة الجنسية .
But while the West has opened on sex,
ولكن في حين انفتاح الغرب على الجنس ,
what we found is that Arab societies appear to have been moving in the opposite direction.
ما وجدناه أن المجتمعات العربية بدت بالتحرك في الاتجاه المعاكس .
In Egypt and many of its neighbors,
في مصر والعديد من جيرانها ,
this closing down is part of a wider closing
وهذا التسكير جزء من التسكيرات الأوسع
in political, social and cultural thought.
في الفكر السياسي والاجتماعي والثقافي .
And it is the product of a complex historical process,
وهي نتاج عملية تاريخية معقدة ,
one which has gained ground with the rise of Islamic conservatism
واحدة حققت قبولا مع صعود التيار الإسلامي المحاقظ
since the late 1970s.
منذ أواخر السبعينات .
"Just say no" is what conservatives around the world
"فقط قل لا " هذا ما كان يقوله المحافظون في أنحاء العالم
say to any challenge to the sexual status quo.
ليتحدوا الوضع الجنسي الراهن .
In the Arab region, they brand these attempts as a Western conspiracy
في المنطقة العربية , وصفت هذه المحاولات بمثابة مؤامرة غربية
to undermine traditional Arab and Islamic values.
لتقويض التقاليد العربية والقيم الإسلامية .
But what's really at stake here
ولكن ما هو حقاً على المحك هنا
is one of their most powerful tools of control:
واحد من الأدوات القوية للتحكم لديهم :
sex wrapped up in religion.
الجنس مغلف بالدين .
But history shows us that even as recently
ولكن التاريخ يبين لنا أنه حتى منذ
as our fathers' and grandfathers' day,
أيام آبائنا وأجدادنا
there have been times of greater pragmatism,
كان هناك وقت للبراغماتية الكبرى ,
and tolerance, and a willingness to consider other interpretations:
والتسامح والاستعداد للنظر في التفسيرات الأخرى :
be it abortion, or masturbation, or even the incendiary topic of homosexuality.
سواء كان ذلك الإجهاض أو ممارسة العادة السرية أو حتى المواضيع الحارقة من الشذوذ الجنسي .
It is not black and white, as conservatives would have us believe.
إنها ليست بالأبيض والأسود كما يحملنا المحافظين على الاعتقاد .
In these, as in so many other matters,
في هذه كما في الكثير من القضايا الأخرى ,
Islam offers us at least 50 shades of gray.
يقدم لنا الإسلام 50 ظل رمادي على الأقل .
(Laughter)
(ضحك )
Over my travels,
خلال رحلاتي ,
I've met men and women across the Arab region
التقيت رجالاً ونساءً من أنحاء المنطقة العربية
who've been exploring that spectrum --
الذين استطلعوا ذلك الطيف --
sexologists who are trying to help couples
المتخصصون في علم الجنس الذين يحاولون مساعدة الأزواج
find greater happiness in their marriages,
ليجدوا قدر أعظم من السعادة في زواجهم ,
innovators who are managing to get sexuality education into schools,
المبتكرون الذين يخططون إلى إدخال الثقافة الجنسية إلى المدارس ,
small groups of men and women,
جماعات صغيرة من النساء والرجال ,
lesbian, gay, transgendered, transsexual,
المثليين ومثليي الجنس والمخنثين والمتحولين جنسيا ,
who are reaching out to their peers
الذين وصلوا إلى أقرانهم
with online initiatives and real-world support.
عن طريق المبادرات عبر الانترنت ودعم في العالم الحقيقي .
Women, and increasingly men, who are starting to speak out
بدأت النساء بالتحدث علنا والرجال كذلك على شكل متزايد
and push back against sexual violence
ليدافعوا ضد العنف الجنسي
on the streets and in the home.
في الشارع وفي المنزل .
Groups that are trying to help sex workers protect themselves against HIV
المجموعات التي تحاول أن تساعد المشتغلين بالجنسن لحماية أنفسهم من فيروس نقص المناعة المكتسب
and other occupational hazards,
وغيرها من الأخطار المهنية ,
and NGOs that are helping unwed mothers like Faiza
والمنظمات غير الحكومية التي تساعد الأمهات غير المتزوجات مثل فايزة
find a place in society, and critically, stay with their kids.
ليجدن مكاناً لهن في المجتمع والبقاء مع أولادهن بشكل حاسم .
Now these efforts are small, they're often underfunded,
هذه الجهود صغيرة حالياوغالبا ما تعاني من نقص في التمويل ,
and they face formidable opposition.
ويواجهون معارضة هائلة .
But I am optimistic that, in the long run,
ولكنني متفائلة بأنه على المدى البعيد ,
times are changing, and they and their ideas
الزمن سيتغير وأفكارهم
will gain ground.
ستصبح متقبلة .
Social change doesn't happen in the Arab region through dramatic confrontation,
التغيير الإجتماعي في المنطقة العربية لا يحدث من خلال المواجهة المثيرة ,
beating or indeed baring of breasts,
الضرب أو في الحقيقة تعرية الثديين ,
but rather through negotiation.
وإنما من خلال التفاوض .
What we're talking here is not about a sexual revolution,
ما نتحدث عنه هنا ليس ثورة جنسية ,
but a sexual evolution, learning from other parts of the world,
وإنما التطور الجنسي والتعلم من أطراف أحرى من العالم ,
adapting to local conditions,
والتكييف مع الظروف المحلية ,
forging our own path, not following one blazed by another.
وتزوير طريقنا وليس اتباع طريق متوهج من قبل الآخرين .
That path, I hope, will one day lead us to the right to control our own bodies,
الطريق الذي أتمناه سيقودنا إلى الصواب لنتحكم بأجسادنا ,
and to access the information and services we need
والوصول إلى المعلومات والخدمات التي نحتاجها
to lead satisfying and safe sexual lives.
ليقودنا إلى الرضا وحياة جنسية آمنة .
The right to express our ideas freely,
الحق بالتعبير عن أفكارنا بحرية ,
to marry whom we choose, to choose our own partners,
لنتزوج الأشخاص الذين اخترناهم , لنختار شركائنا ,
to be sexually active or not, to decide whether to have children and when,
لنكون ناشطين جنسيين أو لا , لنقرر سواء نريد الإنجاب أو لا ومتى نريد ذلك ,
all this without violence or force or discrimination.
كل ذلك بدون عنف أو قوة أو تمييز .
Now we are very far from this across the Arab region,
حالياً نحن بعيدون عن ذلك في المنطقة العربية ,
and so much needs to change:
وهناك حاجة ماسّة لتغيير :
law, education, media, the economy,
القانون , التعليم , الإعلام , الاقتصاد ,
the list goes on and on,
والقائمة تطول وتطول ,
and it is the work of a generation, at least.
وهو عمل جيل على الأقل .
But it begins with a journey that I myself have made,
ولكنها تبدأ برحلة قمت بها بنفسي ,
asking hard questions of received wisdoms
وأنا أسأل أسئلة صعبة بالحكمة المأخوذة
in sexual life.
في الحياة الجنسية .
And it is a journey which has only served to strengthen my faith,
وهي رحلة ساعدتني فقط في تعزيز إيماني ,
and my appreciation of local histories and cultures
وتقديري للتاريخ والثقافات المحلية
by showing me possibilities where I once only saw absolutes.
مما عُرض علي من الاحتمالات في حين كنت أرى المسلمات فقط .
Now given the turmoil in many countries in the Arab region,
حاليا بالنظر إلى الاضرابات في العديد من البلدان في أنجاء المنطقة العربية ,
talking about sex, challenging the taboos,
الحديث عن الجنس وتحدي المحرمات ,
seeking alternatives might sound like something of a luxury.
والبحث عن البدائل قد يبدو وكأنه شيء من الترف .
But at this critical moment in history,
ولكن في هذه اللحظة الحرجة من التاريخ,
if we do not anchor freedom and justice,
إذا لم نرسّخ الحرية والعدالة ,
dignity and equality,
الكرامة والمساواة ,
privacy and autonomy in our personal lives, in our sexual lives,
الخصوصية والاستقلالية في حياتنا الشخصية و في حياتنا الجنسية ,
we will find it very hard to achieve in public life.
سنجد أنه من الصعب جداً تحيقها في الحياة العامة .
The political and the sexual are intimate bedfellows, and that is true for us all.
السياسي والجنسي هم حليفان لصيقان وهذا صحيح بالنسبة لنا جميعاً .
no matter where we live and love.
بغض النظر عن المكان الذي نعيش فيه والذي نحب .
Thank you.
شكرا لكم .
(Applause)
(تصفيق )